## Manuel Duarte de Vasconcelos Silva

**Contact:** 

Mobile: +351 96 4525553

PASS Av. da Liberdade, N.67B 4B

E-mail: madusilva@gmail.com

1250-140 Lisboa Portugal

<a href="https://mdusilva.github.io/">https://mdusilva.github.io/</a><a href="https://github.com/mdusilva">https://github.com/mdusilva</a>

Web:

www.linkedin.com/in/manuel-silva-5191b5149

## Personal profile

For the past two years I have worked as a Data Scientist/Python Developer at PASS, a Lisbon based Fintech startup (<a href="http://www.passp.com/">http://www.passp.com/</a>). The focus of my work has been the development of quantitative based investment models, using Machine Learning/Statistics algorithms, as well as the development of backtesting and automatic order execution software.

Previously I worked as a researcher at CENTRA/SIM (Multidisciplinary Centre for Astrophysics <a href="https://centra.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/">https://centra.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/</a>), developing Data Mining/Machine Learning tools for scientific exploitation of large datasets from the Gaia mission of the European Space Agency (ESA). I have also worked with code for PSF reconstruction in Adaptive Optics in the context of the OPTICON project. Prior to this I was a PhD researcher, modelling the spiral arms of our own Galaxy as traced by runaway stars<sup>1</sup>.

## **Positions**

2018 – Present	Data Scientist / Python Developer
	PASS (http://www.passp.com/), Portugal
2013 – 2017	Researcher
	CENTRA/SIM (https://centra.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/), Portugal
2012	Researcher
	University of Hertfordshire, UK
2006	Sales consultant
	Portugal Telecom, Portugal

## **Projects**

2014 - 2017

## Opticon – "Optical Infrared Co-ordination Network for Astronomy"

- Development and testing of software for PSF reconstruction in Adaptive Optics (GLAO), in the context of the MUSE-GALACSI instrument
- Tasks: coding of Python package; testing (including profiling); implementation
  of performance improvements (multiprocessing, cache); implementation of
  object-oriented interface; write the documentation
- Python 2.7; C; json; FITS 3.0

<sup>1</sup> http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21729044.000

## 2013 - 2014

# Gaia: National Participation in the Data Processing and Analysis Consortium (DPAC)

- Development of data mining/machine learning software for estimation of stellar parameters in large databases in the context of the European Space Agency's (ESA) mission Gaia
- Tasks: coding of two Python packages; implementation of Bayesian inference algorithms; implementation of distributed computing solutions (execute package; Hadoop/Spark); testing; write the documentation
- Python 2.7/3.6; json

## **Education**

# 2007 – 2011

## PhD in Astrophysics - University of Herfordshire, UK

- Thesis: Runaway Stars in the Galactic Halo: Their Origin and Kinematics
- Supervisor: Dr Ralf Napiwotzki

## 2004 - 2006

## Master degree in Statistics - Universidade do Porto, Portugal

- Thesis: *Um processo de risco perturbado: aproximações numéricas à probabilidade de ruína*
- Supervisor: Dra Margarida Brito
- Topics:
  - Stochastic processes
  - Machine learning
  - Multivariate statistics
- Final grade: "Muito Bom" (Very Good)

## 1998 - 2004

# First degree in Astrophysics (Physics/Applied Mathematics) – Universidade do Porto, Portugal

Final grade: 13

## **Publications**

- [1] Silva M. D. V. & Napiwotzki R., "High Galactic latitude runaway stars as tracers of the spiral arms", 2013, MNRAS, 431, 502-510 Astro-ph: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1302.0761v1">http://arxiv.org/abs/1302.0761v1</a>
- [2] Napiwotzki R. & Silva M. D. V., "Runaway and hypervelocity stars. The supernova connection", 2012, MEMORIE della Società Astronomica Italiana Astro-ph: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1109.4116">http://arxiv.org/abs/1109.4116</a>
- [3] Silva M. D. V. & Napiwotzki R., "Ejection velocities of high Galactic latitude runaway stars", 2011, MNRAS, 411, 2596 Astro-ph: http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.3651

## IT skills

#### General:

- OS administration/scripting (Linux and Windows)
- Git/Github
- Visual Studio Code
- misc. applications: Tex, Gimp, Photoshop, MS Office (Word, Excel, Access)

## **Developed packages:**

- rpsfpy: software in Python for PSF reconstruction in Adaptive Optics
- Pysysp: Python package for synthetic stellar photometry: <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pysysp/1.0.1">https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pysysp/1.0.1</a>
- MASS: Massive MCMC sampler (Bayesian inference): https://github.com/mdusilva/mass
- Mamuto: Python package for distributed computing in clusters: <a href="https://github.com/mdusilva/mamuto">https://github.com/mdusilva/mamuto</a>

### **Programming:**

- Python, R, C# / .NET, MATLAB, Fortran 90
- parallel/distributed computing: Spark, Hadoop, MPI

#### **Databases:**

• MySQL, Postgres SQL, SQLite, Python-SQL, PL/SQL

## Web:

• Typescript, Jekyll, Apache Web servers (configuration)

## Python:

- Data Science: XGBoost, scikit-learn, Pandas, SPAMS (dictionary learning)
- Visualization/dashboards: dash, Plotly, seaborn
- distributed computing: ZeroMQ, pyspark, execnet
- Web: Flask, requests
- Databases: SQLAlchemy
- Bayesian inference (MCMC): pymc

## Languages

Fluent: Portuguese, English

Good understanding: French, Spanish

Basic Greek and German (level A1 certificate)

# Other interests

I am a qualified Futsal referee. I like to play Football and Futsal, playing chess, Philosophy, travelling. I am also engaged in Science outreach activities directed at the general public.